<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<aiml version="1.0">
    <!-- Last modified 8-13-12020 by VaryAble -->

    <category>
        <pattern>Is it the i or the e first</pattern>
        <template>
            This is a spelling question that troubles even the best spellers
            out there from time to time. The old rule "i before e except after
            c" will help you sometimes, but not in all cases. Some important
            notes should include "or when sounded like a, like neighbor
            and weigh" and the rule should be dropped altogether when -c
            sounds like -sh, as in species.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How is a paper organized</pattern>
        <template>
            Being able to organize an essay, research project or story is an
            essential part to doing well in any area of academics. While there
            are, of course, many subtleties, a paper should start with an
            introductory paragraph containing a thesis–the most important part
            of any essay. After this, each paragraph should have a main idea
            followed by information that expands on and explains these ideas.
            At the end, work should be tied up with a conclusion paragraph. It
            sounds basic, but many students let their writing become sloppier
            as they go along or never develop these strong fundamentals in the
            first place.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>Which is the subject and which is the object</pattern>
        <template>
            If you don’t remember which part of the sentence is which, you’re
            not alone. In most basic terms, you can remember that the subject
            is the part of the sentence that is doing something, while the
            object is the thing that is having something done to it. This can
            be helpful to know when learning a language besides English, as
            well.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is a pronoun</pattern>
        <template>
            Most of us know what a noun is a person, place, or thing, but do you recall what a pronoun
            is? Pronouns are the words that take the place of nouns in a
            sentence including I, she, he, it, you, we and they. Using these
            correctly may get a bit trickier but you can always ask me.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is a homonym antonym and a synonym</pattern>
        <template>
            A homonym is a group of words that appear to be the same but
            actually have different meanings or pronunciations. An antonym
            refers to a word that is the opposite in meaning from another
            word. A synonym is a word that means the same or similar as
            another word.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is the correct way to use commas</pattern>
        <template>
            Commas aren't alone in often being used incorrectly. Semi-colons,
            hyphens and colons are frequently used incorrectly as well. If you
            find it hard to remember to use these elements of speech
            correctly, reference a guide like this until you can commit it to
            memory.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What’s the difference between its and it’s</pattern>
        <template>
            Find yourself often mixing these two up? You’re certainly not
            alone but there’s an easy way to remember which is the right word
            for the situation. Simply remind yourself that "it’s" is a
            contraction of the words "it is." If the expanded form of those
            words doesn’t make sense in your sentence, then you know to use
            "its" rather than "it’s".
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How can you tell if a sentence is too long or too short</pattern>
        <template>
            Sentences can either be a run-on or a fragment. You can determine
            if your sentence is a run-on by simply turning it into a yes or no
            question. If it makes sense, you’re doing ok. If not, you need to
            add some kind of conjunction or separate it into two sentences. A
            fragment on the other hand is simply an incomplete sentence that
            doesn’t make sense on it’s own. You can usually fix these by
            adding them back onto the main sentence to which they refer.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are a verse stanza and paragraph</pattern>
        <template>
            In most cases, a verse is a single line of poetry, though more
            loosely it is a series of words arranged metrically. A stanza is a
            group of these verses, usually composed of four or more that work
            together in a poem or a song. A paragraph, on the other hand, is a
            division within a written work that focuses on a particular idea
            found in prose rather than poetic works.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What things need to be capitalized</pattern>
        <template>
            While you’re probably aware that things like names, titles and
            other proper nouns need to be capitalized, are you aware of what
            parts of a book title should be capitalized or whether or not to
            capitalize the names of the seasons? Here you’ll find information
            on just about everything you should or shouldn’t put into caps.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the state capitals</pattern>
        <template>
            Unless you use this information regularly, it’s easy to forget
            what the capital of far flung states are. It can be good to know
            these kinds of things, however, so use this online table to
            review. If you get ambitious, learn the capitals of other
            countries as well.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are longitude and latitude</pattern>
        <template>
            Longitudinal lines are those that go around the globe vertically
            (you can remember them as being long like hair) and latitudinal
            lines are those that go around horizontally like the equator.
            These lines allow every place on earth to be specified using just
            three coordinates and aid in navigation.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What factors led to the Revolutionary War</pattern>
        <template>
            Taxation without representation is a phrase you should remember
            from your elementary education days. Taxes imposed on the colonies
            by the British on goods like sugar and documents enraged the
            public who felt that if they were gong to be taxed they should at
            least have some kind of representation in the British Parliament.
            These factors, among many much more complex issues, led the early
            American people to revolt against British rule.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How are laws made</pattern>
        <template>
            Not sure how the regulations we have came to be? The process takes
            a little explaining so you can read about it here or watch the
            classic Schoolhouse Rocks video of how a bill gets made into a
            law.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>
            What are the branches of the government and what do they do
        </pattern>
        <template>
            The government is composed of three branches: the legislative, the
            judicial and the executive. The legislative branch is made up of
            the Senate and the House of Representatives. These individuals are
            responsible for debating, proposing and signing bills into law.
            The judicial branch refers to the court system, headed up by the
            Supreme Court. This branch decides how to apply the laws, whether
            or not they are constitutional and how they should be interpreted.
            Finally, the executive branch is composed of the president, vice
            president, cabinet members and various other supporting
            institutions. This branch carries out laws, suggests new ones and
            runs national defense and foreign policies.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is Manifest Destiny</pattern>
        <template>
            This term, coined in the 19th century, refers to the belief that
            Americans were destined, perhaps even divinely so, to expand
            across the continent from the Atlantic Ocean to the Pacific. This
            term was used to justify the harsh, and often violent, means
            implemented in an effort to bring the rest of North America under
            US control.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the major amendments to the Constitution</pattern>
        <template>
            The first ten amendments to the Constitution are collectively
            known as the Bill of Rights. These include the right to free
            speech, the right to bear arms, the right to trial, and many more
            basic freedoms we often take for granted. Other important
            amendments include the 13th which abolished slavery, the 15th
            which gave non-whites the right to vote, the 19th giving women the
            right to vote, the 22nd limiting the president to two terms, and
            the 18th and 21st prohibiting (and then allowing) the sale and
            consumption of alcohol.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What were the 13 original colonies</pattern>
        <template>
            The 13 colonies were Massachusetts, Rhode Island, New Hampshire,
            New York, Virginia, Connecticut, Delaware, New Jersey,
            Pennsylvania, Maryland, North Carolina, South Carolina, and
            Georgia.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the names of the Great Lakes</pattern>
        <template>
            The Great Lakes are composed of five large bodies of water: Erie,
            Huron, Michigan, Superior and Ontario, containing a whopping 5
            percent of the world’s fresh water.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>Who wrote the Declaration of Independence</pattern>
        <template>
            While there were several contributors to this piece of writing,
            the primary author was Thomas Jefferson, using the statement to
            declare that the 13 colonies were no longer under the rule of the
            British Empire.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>Why do the seasons change</pattern>
        <template>
            If you ask most people, they’ll say it has something to do with
            the Earth’s distance from the sun. However, this is actually not
            why the seasons occur. The real reason is that the Earth spins on
            a tilted axis, causing different parts of the Earth to point
            towards the sun at different times of the year. This allows more
            sun to reach these areas at a more direct angle, causing the
            warmer and cooler temperatures that we experience as the seasons.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What’s the difference between mitosis and meiosis</pattern>
        <template>
            Mitosis it is the basic way that cells of all kinds reproduce,
            creating two cells from one that are identical copies of the
            original parent cell. Meiosis on the other hand, is what happens
            in gamete or sex cells, producing cells with half the number of
            chromosomes as the parent cell and creating four cells from the
            original one.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What the heck do mitochondria do</pattern>
        <template>
            You may have forgotten the parts of the cell, but the mitochondria
            is an important component, providing your cells with the energy
            they need to do what a cell needs to do, often being referred to
            as the powerhouse of the cell.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How are animal and plant cells different</pattern>
        <template>
            Animal and plant cells are alike in many ways but have some key
            differences that allow them to create such a diverse group of
            organisms. One difference is the lack of a thick cell wall in
            animal cells. Plants need this cell wall to keep from bursting.
            Perhaps the biggest difference between plant and animal cells is
            their source of energy. Plants gather light from the sun and
            convert it to energy through photosynthesis, while animal cells
            use sugars and other substances that they consume to power
            themselves. Additionally, plant and animal cells differ in the
            size, shape and number of their vacuoles, and plant cells tend to
            have a set shape while animal cells can differ greatly.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the phases of the moon</pattern>
        <template>
            The moon starts off at the new moon where no light is visible.
            From there it grows through the waxing crescent, first quarter,
            and waxing gibbous into a full moon. After a full moon, the light
            dwindles through the waning gibbous, third quarter, and waning
            crescent back to the new moon.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the types of clouds</pattern>
        <template>
            While there are many subdivisions of clouds, the main types are:
            cumulus (the puffy, fluffy clouds); stratus (horizontal, layered
            clouds); and cirrus (wispy, feathery clouds). Add the word
            "nimbus" onto any of these to denote a cloud that produces rain,
            hail or snow.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is the order of the planets</pattern>
        <template>
            While many of us learned that there are nine planets, today there
            are only eight, as Pluto is no longer included. The remaining
            eight comprise of: Mercury, Venus, Earth, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn,
            Uranus and Neptune.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How does weather work</pattern>
        <template>
            Weather is a complex thing, but something that students begin
            learning about in school from an early age. Watch the animation
            found on this site to learn why weather changes or stays the same.
            You can also refresh your memory on the water cycle here.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How do we know the Earth’s crust isn’t solid</pattern>
        <template>
            While the ground you’re standing on might seem solid, any fifth
            grader can tell you that it’s simply an arrangement of plates
            making up the outer crust. We can see and feel these plates move
            through earthquakes and can look back in history to find that the
            continents themselves have moved around over millions of years.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How does gravity work</pattern>
        <template>
            While there are two different interpretations of gravity
            (Einstein’s and Newton’s), we’ll stick with the basics here.
            Gravity is the natural tendency for objects with mass to attract
            one another. In our case, this object is Earth, which, in being
            much larger than us, pulls us to the ground and keeps us firmly
            earth bound.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What’s osmosis</pattern>
        <template>
            As a kid you probably hoped you could learn through this process
            rather than doing your homework, but you may have long since
            forgotten the meaning. Osmosis is the process by which water is
            diffused into a cell body through a semi-permeable membrane,
            moving water from an area of high saturation to one of low
            saturation, much like a sponge picking up a spill or water seeping
            into a basement.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How do reflexes work</pattern>
        <template>
            A reflex is an involuntary reaction that your body has in response
            to a stimulus, like pulling your hand away from a hot surface.
            Reflexes are controlled by the spinal cord, which takes over,
            sending a message to your muscle via the nerves that tells it to
            react. Reflexes can include things like coughing, breathing and
            sneezing as well.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is the scapula</pattern>
        <template>
            The scapula is the scientific name for the shoulder blade, one of
            206 bones in the human body.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the steps of the scientific method</pattern>
        <template>
            If you want to figure something out using science, you’d follow
            these steps of the scientific method: ask a question, do research,
            form a hypothesis, test your hypothesis with an experiment,
            analyze your data and draw a conclusion, and finally, report your
            results.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>Who laid out the Laws of Motion</pattern>
        <template>
            The Laws of Motion (regarding force, inertia and other basics of
            physics) were laid out by Sir Isaac Newton in 1687 and form the
            foundation of classical mechanics.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the parts of an atom</pattern>
        <template>
            There are three components to an atom: the protons (positively
            charged particles); the neutrons (particles with no charge); and
            numerous electrons (the negatively charged particles).
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>How many feet are in a mile</pattern>
        <template>
            American students have it rough using measurements that are hard
            to remember because they’re so oddly numbered. There are 12 inches
            in a foot, three feet in a yard, 1760 yards in a mile. That means
            there’s a whopping 5280 feet to a mile.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the different types of numbers</pattern>
        <template>
            There are several different groups numbers can fall into. Natural
            numbers (the counting numbers), whole numbers (add a zero to the
            natural numbers), and integers (this group throws negatives into
            the mix as well). Additionally, there are rational numbers
            (integers with the addition of fractions) and irrational (numbers
            that can’t be represented as fractions like pi and some square
            roots). Of course, there are other groups as well, but these are
            the basics.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is a prime number</pattern>
        <template>
            In math-speak, a prime number is a number that has two integer
            factors, one and itself. More plainly speaking, it’s a number that
            can’t be divided evenly by any number other than one and itself.
            Some examples of prime numbers are 2, 3, 5, 7, and 11, though the
            list goes on and on.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>Just what is the order of operations</pattern>
        <template>
            This order can be remembered as PEMDAS: parentheses, exponents,
            multiplication, division, addition, and subtraction. This order
            will allow you to get the correct answer when working with complex
            equations.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What’s a mean median mode and range</pattern>
        <template>
            The mean is the average of a group of numbers, the median is the
            middle value in a list of numbers put in numerical order, the mode
            is the most commonly occurring number and the range is the
            difference between the largest and smallest values in the list.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the types of triangles</pattern>
        <template>
            Triangles can be put into several categories: right (having one
            right angle); equilateral (all angles are 60 degrees); isosceles
            (having two equal angles and two equal sides); scalene (having no
            sides the same); acute (all angles are less than 90 degrees); and
            obtuse (the triangle has one angle larger than 90 degrees).
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What happens when you multiply two negatives</pattern>
        <template>
            Negative numbers can get tricky. When you multiply two of them,
            you should end up with a positive number. Additionally, when you
            subtract a negative number from any other number the negative
            number is treated as an addition of a positive one.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>Can you divide by zero</pattern>
        <template>
            Hopefully you remembered you cannot divide by zero. Any attempt to
            divide by zero, even to divide zero by zero, results in an
            undefined result that isn’t much use to anyone.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>The Arts</pattern>
        <template>Here you’ll find the basics for music and the arts.</template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the notes on the scale</pattern>
        <template>
            The basic notes on a scale are C, D, E, F, G, A and B in that
            order, though there are sharps, flats and other variations to
            these notes.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are the types of notes</pattern>
        <template>
            Chances are good that you used these notes in a childhood music
            class, but you may have forgotten them, unless you still play an
            instrument. The basic types of notes are whole, half, quarter,
            eighth and sixteenth which you can see in this picture. Each type
            of note tells you how many of it will appear in each measure.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is the style of art Picasso is best known for</pattern>
        <template>
            Picasso worked his way through a variety of artistic styles in his
            decades of production but is perhaps best known for his work with
            Cubism. Cubism distorts space and forms, leaving works that often
            have recognizable elements that have been twisted and fractured.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What is the difference between high and bas relief</pattern>
        <template>
            These represent different levels of relief. High relief art stands
            out from its surface, often having elements that are not attached
            at all. Bas relief on the other hand, is an extremely low relief,
            barely standing out on the surface.
        </template>
    </category>
    <category>
        <pattern>What are complementary colors</pattern>
        <template>
            The basic colors on the color wheel are red, blue, yellow, purple,
            orange and green. Of these colors, the complementary ones are
            those that opposite to one another–blue and orange, red and green
            and yellow and purple. When two complementary colors are mixed
            they create a neutral color like gray or black.
        </template>
    </category>
</aiml>
      